Gertrude Claus Collection of Goodall-Sanford, Inc., Photographs 6664 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gertrude Claus Collection of Goodall-Sanford, Inc., Photographs
1952
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gertrude Claus
Goodall-Sanford, Inc.
6664 P
0.61 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
Photographs documenting the production of wool cloth.
10065317
Biographical / Historical
The Goodall Woolen Mills were founded in Sanford, Maine, by Thomas Goodall in 1867. Some of the plant's early production included railroad car upholstery, carpets, draperies, auto fabrics, and clothing fabric under the name "Palm Beach." The mills underwent a modernization phase in 1910. The Goodal family ran the company until it was sold to the Burlington Mills Corporation in 1953. In 1955 Burlington closed the mills.
Scope and Contents
Photographs show spinning machines, gilling machines the worsted yarn preparation is shown at different stages of the process at the Goodall-Sanford Mills in Sanford, Maine. Also includes photographs from the U.S. Department of Agriculture documenting wool processing.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 12, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 07, 2017
Carding; Drying apparatus; Dyes and dyeing; Engraving; Women employees; Male employees; Looms; Spinning machinery; Textile factories; Textile printing; Measuring the performance of textiles -- textile testing; Textile workers; Textile machinery; Weaving; Winding machines; Women textile workers; Wool; Wool scouring; Wool-carding; Wool-combing; Woolen and worsted drawing; Woolen and worsted finishing; Woolen and worsted machinery; Woolen and worsted manufacture; Woolen and worsted spinning; Reweaving; Arlington Mills; Birch Brothers, Inc.; Goodall-Sanford, Inc. (Sanford, Me.); U.S. Department of Agriculture
10065317
- Aerial View of Plant and Interior Views Sorting and Cleaning Operations, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aerial view of Goodall-Sanford, Inc., Sanford, Maine, ATHM# 1990.85.1, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts an aerial view of the Goodall-Sanford, Inc., plant in Sanford, Me. Plant is in foreground, consisting of several multi-story buildings. Residential houses spread out behind plant, with open area in background and mountains visible in distant background.
  - Sorting, ATHM# 1990.85.2, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts an older man sorting wool. A large bag of wool is on the floor near him, with open wooden bins of wool behind him. Text: "Sorting. The shorn fleece from a sheep (wool) and the fleece from the Angora goat (mohair) contain sections of coarse, medium, and fine fibers. Skilled tradesmen, known as "sorters," separate these sections by hand into various sorts."
  - Blended Sorts, ATHM# 1990.85.3, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts large piles of wool on a warehouse floor. Large windows in the rear give light. Text: "Blended Sorts. After sorting, the same grades from each sorter are carefully blended and spread over a large floor area to make a uniform blend. These various lots are carefully placed in layers to obtain uniform quality within each lot. Thus, when the wool or mohair is started through the processing, any variances in the judgment of the sorters will be equalized and a uniform yarn will result."
  - Scouring, ATHM# 1990.85.4, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts large piles of wool being put through a scouring machine. Text: "Scouring. The operation of scouring is to remove foreign matter from the raw wool and mohair. The fibers are passed through various scouring bowls containing soaps and chemicals; squeezed between rolls by hydraulic pressure; and finally run through a continuous dryer and deposited in large trucks ready to be taken to the next operation."
  - Carding, ATHM# 1990.85.5, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 26.5 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts wool carding machines in operation. There is a large bin of wool in the foreground. Text: "Carding. The scoured wool or mohair is placed into hoppers from which predetermined amounts are passed through a series of wire-covered cylinders. These cylinders turn at high speed in opposite directions, thereby straightening and paralleling the fibers so that they can be formed into a thin web. This web, condensed, results in a heavy sliver of parallel fibers."
  - Combing, ATHM# 1990.85.6, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 26.5 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the combing process of wool slivers. Note the pile of finished coils on the left. Text: "Combing. This process removes shorter fibers below a desired length for worsted processing. It combs the longer fibers which are retained and arranges them in parallel order. During this combing operation, neps and other impurities, which have not been previously removed, are also taken out with the shorter fibers. The short fibers, called noils, are the basis for blends in woolen yarn production."
  - Finished Gilling, ATHM# 1990.85.7, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts combed slivers being processed through a gill box. Text: "Finished Gilling. A number of combed slivers are processed through the gill box which further parallels the fiber mass by means of drafting rolls and fallers. These fallers consist of a number of tapered pins which move at a faster surface speed, thus performing a combing action."
  - Drawing (Mix Gill), ATHM# 1990.85.8, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 19.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 19.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts combed slivers being reduced to a fine roving through the process of drawing. Text: "Drawing (Mix Gill). After combing and top making, it is necessary to further blend the various fiber components and to reduce the heavy sliver down to a relatively fine roving which can be used on the spinning frame. Here we have an overall view of some of the drawing operations. The first operation is the Mix Gill. Here we see a number of tops blended and drafted through fallers to further blend and parallel the fibers."
  - Drawing (Two Spindle Gill Box), ATHM# 1990.85.9, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the process of drawing the blended slivers onto spools as slubbing. Text: "Drawing (Two Spindle Gill Box). Thoroughly blended and mixed slivers are run together, drafted and wrapped onto large spools as slubbing. From this point all slubbing will be reduced in size, twist inserted and wrapped onto spools."
  - Drawing Operations, ATHM# 1990.85.10, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 21 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a row of drawing frames. Text: "Drawing Operations. A general view showing the frames and manner in which the stock is drawn down to size and wrapped onto spools."
- Drawing, Spinning, and Winding, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drawing (Six Spindle Weigh Box), ATHM# 1990.85.11, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a six spindle weigh box that is further reducing the product as part of the drawing operation. Text: "Drawing (Six Spindle Weigh Box). The product coming from the two-spindle gill box is further reduced in size on this machine."
  - Drawing (Eight Spindle Reducer), ATHM# 1990.85.12, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts an eight-spindle reducer that further reduces the product as part of the drawing operation. Only six spindles can be seen in this photo, with the seventh partially visible on the right. Text: "Drawing (Eight Spindle Reducer). The product taken off the six-spindle weigh box is again reduced in size on this eight- spindle reducer."
  - Drawing (Twelve Spindle Finisher), ATHM# 1990.85.13, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a twelve spindle finisher, the final operation in drawing. Text: "Drawing (Twelve Spindle Finisher). This is the final operation in heavy drawing. Its product will be supplied to the Roving Frame (Rover)." See item 4 in this folder.
  - Rover, ATHM# 1990.85.14, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts roving frames. The frame in the right foreground was manufactured by Prince Smith & Son of Keighley, England. Text: "Rover. These frames produce the roving by finally drafting the product of the 12-spindle finisher to the size required for the spinning operation."
  - Ring Spinning, ATHM# 1990.85.15, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount). (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a large room of spinning frames. Text: "Ring Spinning. The spools at the top of the frames contain what is known as roving. This roving is reduced in size through a set of rolls and wound onto bobbins revolving at high speed. In the operation of spinning, the amount of twist is controlled to give the resultant product the desired characteristics; namely, loftiness, strength, smoothness, resiliency, etc."
  - Ring Spinning [Close-up View], ATHM# 1990.85.16, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount). (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male textile worker standing next to a ring spinning frame. Text: "Ring Spinning. This shows a close-up view of the ring spinning frame. On the top of the machine the roving will be seen as it passes through a series of rolls driven at varying speeds."
  - Cap Spinning, ATHM# 1990.85.17, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a line of cap spinning frames. Cap spinning is a different process from ring spinning and is used more often for spinning worsted yarns. Text: "Cap Spinning. Yarn produced by this process is spun with the aid of metal caps which differ from the rings. This process produces yarn of a different character which may be desired in certain fabrics."
  - Automatic Winder, ATHM# 1990.85.18, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount). (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts an automatic winder. Text: "Automatic Winder. Bobbins of yarn taken from the spinning frame are usually of relatively small size. In order to increase the efficiency of the subsequent operation, these bobbins are wound on larger packages. The winder automatically feeds bobbins into the machine as the yarn runs out and ties the yarn to the larger package. All the operator has to do is remove the large package from the machine, which is then ready for the next operation."
  - Twisting, ATHM# 1990.85.19, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts twisting machines. Text: "Twisting. For certain fabrics two-ply yarns are required. Therefore, single yarns, as they come from the spinning frame, have to be plied and twisted. In this twisting operation two ends of single yarn are combined, twisted, and wound onto bobbins."
  - Ply Winding, ATHM# 1990.85.20, 1952; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts winders. Yarn from the smaller bobbins is wound into larger packages, seen at the top of the machines. Text: "Ply Winding. The two-ply yarns, as received from the twister, are wound onto large packages in order to increase the efficiency of subsequent operations."
- Winding, Beaming, Slashing, and Weaving, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Filling Winding, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a room of winding machines. Note the row of bins placed beneath the machines to receive the filled bobbins. Text: "Filling Winding. In order to prepare filling yarn for weaving, it has to be wound on quills or filling bobbins. The yarn is wound from large packages onto wooden quills in such a manner that all of them are of the same diameter so that they will fit into the shuttle. This winder performs the operation automatically, that is, as a bobbin is filled it drops into a container placed under the machine. An empty bobbin is then automatically placed onto the winding mechanism, and the winder again starts operating." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 2: Jackspooling, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a room where female employees inspect the yarn for defects before it is wound onto spools. Each woman sits in front of a spooler inspecting numerous yarns as they pass over an inspection board in front of her. Text: "Jackspooling. Large yarn packages are placed in a creel behind each spooler. These individual yarns are pased over an inspection board to be observed for yarn defects. The yarns are ultimately wound on jack-spools at the bottom of the frame." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 3: Section Beaming, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the process of section beaming. Ten jackspools are combined to make one section beam. Note the size of the jackspools at the rear of the machine in contrast to the size of the beam being created at the front. Text: "Section Beaming. Usually 10 jackspools are combined to make one section beam of 400 ends. The yarns are run over lease rods and through a comb to get them straight on the section beam." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 4: Slashing, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee standing by a slasher, a machine that applies a sizing mixture to warp yarns. The sized and dried yarns are being wound onto a loom beam in the foreground. Text: "Slashing. Depending upon the amount of warp ends required for a fabric, a number of section beams are set up on a creel behind the slasher. These yarns are then passed through a size box containing starch solution of carefully controlled temperature. After the size has been applied, the yarn is run through squeeze rolls and then passed over hot steam pipes to dry. The yarns are then passed over and under lease rods also through a comb to keep them straight for winding on a loom beam." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 5: Drawing-In, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a female employee drawing in threads through a heddle. Text: "Drawing-In. Before a loom beam is placed into a loom, each thread must be drawn through a heddle. The heddle is a small metal rod having an eye in the center of it. These heddles are held by a frame or harness. Several harnesses are used in one weave; therefore, the operator must be exceedingly careful to draw the thread through the proper heddle. As these harnesses are lifted in the loom, the threads are raised allowing the shuttle to pass between them thus forming the required weave." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 6: Weaving, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts male and female employees at work in a room full of looms. The "greige goods" referred to in the text simply mean cloth as it leaves the loom before any kind of finishing or bleaching treatment. Text: "Weaving. This process is the art of interlacing warp and filling yarns to form pieces of fabric. As these pieces of greige goods are woven, they are removed from the loom for subsequent finishing operations." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 7: Mending, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a young woman seated in front of a board on which cloth is spread, mending any flaws in the cloth,. Text: "Mending. Skilled operators must correct all yarn and weave imperfections. In some cases these yarns have to be removed and sewn in again by hand. Knots are pulled to the back of the material to obtain a fabric with a perfectly finished face." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 8: Crabbing, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee standing by a crabbing machine. The "greige goods" referred to in the text simply means cloth that has come off the loom but has not yet been bleached or finished in any way. The steam is visible, as are the rollers through which the cloth is pulled. Text: "Crabbing. This process of passing greige goods through boiling water in open width under tension sets the warp and filling threads; thereby preventing the formation of cockles, creases, or other forms of uneven shrinkage in the finished fabric." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 9: Singeing, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a singeing machine. This machine appears to have been manufactured by Birch Brothers, Inc. of Somerville, Mass.; Birch Brothers manufactured textile dyeing and finishing machinery. Text: "Singeing. Fabrics as received from the loom contain fibers which protrude from top and bottom surfaces. These fibers must be removed to obtain a smooth fabric. The two methods most commonly used are passing the fabric at high speed over a hot gas flame, or over a superheated copper bar. This operation removes the protruding fibers." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 10: Tint Removal, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the machinery involved in the process of tint removal. Text: "Tint Removal. Yarns containing varying percentages of different fibers must be tinted for identification purposes. This fugitive tint has to be removed prior to any subsequent finishing operation. The machine shown removes this fugitive tint by passing the fabric through a number of bowls containing chemicals." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
- Inspection and Development, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Continuous Scouring, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a long line of scouring machines. Text: "Continuous Scouring. In this operation miles of fabric are being washed in a continuous process to prepare for dyeing and subsequent finishing operations." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 2: Continuous Scouring [Close-up View], 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a closer view of the scouring machines and the fabric as it is reeled from one machine to another. Text: "Continuous Scouring. A close-up view of the fabric being scoured in the continuous operation." 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 21 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 3: Vigoureux Printing, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a printing machine where the slivers are printed, rather than finished cloth being printed,. Text: "Vigoureux Printing. For special types of color mixtures a number of slivers of top are passed through a printing machine. This machine transfers color by means of evenly spaced bars onto the top, thus creating harmonious color effects when this top is processed through subsequent operations." 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.25 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 4: Kettle Dyeing, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a room filled with dyeing kettles. Several male employees are visible, one at the controls of one of the kettles, one standing by the kettles, and one standing next to a cart loaded with fabric. Text: "Kettle Dyeing. A number of pieces of fabric are continually rotated through dye solutions within these stainless steel kettles. Dyeing is one of the most important of all finishing operations and requires specialists having chemical and technical training and experience. In order to obtain the desired shade and color fastness requirements, selection of dye-stuffs, chemicals, and temperatures must be carefully controlled and supervised." 25.5 x 21cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 21 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 5: Kettle Dyeing [Close-up View], 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a close-up view of fabric as it goes through a dyeing kettle. Text: "Kettle Dyeing. Here we have a close-up of a stainless steel piece dye kettle. The pieces are laid over a stainless steel creel which revolves, thus continually changing the position of the pieces. This is necessary to get uniform dye penetration." 25.5 x 20.5cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 6: Mill Dye Laboratory, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts an overhead view of several male employees at work in the mill dye laboratory. Visible are jars of chemicals, a fan, a hot plate, and other equipment to test the dyes. Text: "Mill Dye Laboratory. This Laboratory is used primarily as a control department directly in conjunction with the Dye House to determine if production meets the rigid quality standards set up for the individual styles." 25.5 x 20.5cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 7: Fabric Dryer, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a fabric dryer to properly dry wet fabrics. Text: "Fabric Dryer. Wet processed fabrics must be dried to control shrinkage lengthwise and widthwise. This machine is mechanically constructed to accomplish this purpose." 25.5 x 20.5cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 8: Full Decating, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)